[Music]
i see you as a very unique source for a
couple of reasons because i see you as
someone who has experience with
obviously
whistleblowing and what's going on with
um our cia in the military
but also a real inside um side view
of what it's like to be incarcerated in
this country and see from inside what
the criminal justice system is here
and i can't help but see parallels
between when you talk about like torture
that we do to
um people across the globe i can't help
but draw parallels to how we treat our
inmates that are incarcerated in a lot
of cases
and so i i was i was wondering if you
could talk about
um examples of that you might have seen
or that you know of where our system
here in this country
is what we would consider to be acting
amorally in how we treat our
incarcerated citizens
we don't have time for that conversation
no okay
i'll give you a couple examples um
what i'm right is that if there is a
parallel like it's the same thing
you are 100 right so listen the united
nations has declared
our use of solitary confinement to be a
form of torture
right international standards are that
someone can't be held in solitary
confinement
confinement for more than 14 days we
have prisoners who have been
in solitary confinement and i mean
solitary
no contact with another human being for
more than
40 years 40 years
you lose your mind after a couple of
months yeah
i think to me when you say 14 days i
think that
you know to me two or three days would
feel like 14 days
if you're you're sleeping on a on a
steal slab
with a small sink and a toilet uh your
room is six by ten feet
and all you can do is walk in circles
you know they say that you
are allowed one hour of exercise every
day that it's 23 hours of solitary
that's nonsense what that one hour of
exercise is
that there's a steel door at the back of
your of your cell
and it leads out into a cage that's
another six by ten feet
and so you can walk in a little circle
outside for one hour
and that's it it's still solitary so you
have people
losing their minds constantly and don't
forget that
that psychological studies that have
been published as recently as
as a year and a half ago have found
that 85 percent of incarcerated
americans
suffer from some sort of mental illness
most commonly antisocial personality
disorder
so you're already kind of on the edge
besides the fact that everybody in
prison is
depressed lots of people are bipolar
some are schizophrenic
we used to have this thing called zombie
pill line where
you know if you need if you need insulin
you get in line at six am and six pm and
they give you your insulin but if you're
insane
you get in line at seven pm and you get
your pills that turn you into a zombie
and so we called it zombie pill line
there was a guy
in solitary confinement in my prison who
had been in for so long and was so
desperate to get out
that he smashed the window of the cell
and ate the broken glass and then he
called for help and he said i ate broken
glass and they told him
tough luck well the glass shredded his
stomach
and he ended up bleeding to death and
that kind of thing happens
all the time i'll give you another
example
um when i first got to prison i went to
my case manager and i said listen i've
got a master's degree
in middle eastern studies policy
analysis i
i did my phd coursework in international
affairs i'd be happy to
teach a ged class uh if if you want me
to
can i swear on this show absolutely
and he looked at me and he said kiriakou
if i want you to teach a
[__] class i'll ask you to teach a
[__] class
and they made me a janitor in the chapel
that was my job i think a lot of this
a lot of this also goes to the
privatization
and the profit motive um
in private prisons this was a federal
prison so
this was government but you're right the
private far worse because of the profit
motive
the only way they can make a profit is
to cut back on food
and on medicine remind me of that i'm
going to come back to that in a moment
so um i was in the
um in the chapel
and every day i would walk past this one
guy's
cell he was an older italian guy
and i liked him i liked all the italians
so
he was kind of doubled over one day and
i said hey man what's wrong
he said man my back is killing me like
really killing me i
can't sleep or anything and i said oh
you should go to the uh
you should go to the the medical unit he
goes down there and they
did what they do for everybody no matter
what your complaint is they gave him
tylenol
and then i saw him i don't know a couple
weeks later and he had a walker
and i said is your back that bad and he
said
i feel like i'm paralyzed and he said
every time i go to medical they give me
a they give me tylenol
so a couple of more weeks pass and
i see him in a wheelchair so i went to
the chaplain and i said chaplin
you've got to do something about this
they're not paying any attention to him
at medical and something is clearly
wrong with him
so the chaplain to his credit weighed in
the chaplain was the only decent human
being i met
in in the entire system and um
so he went and he said something to
medical and finally
after like six weeks medical took him
out to a hospital
for an x-ray and he had stage four
spinal cancer and
he applied for a compassionate release
so that he could die at home
the warden went to his cell and told him
that if he would sign a paper
saying that um that they treated him
appropriately
in medical they would let him go
well he knew he was a dead man he only
had a couple of days left
and he wanted his wife and his children
to be able to sue the system
for killing him which is what they did
and he refused to sign
and they wouldn't let him go he died in
his bunk
and then that's typical of what's going
on there
yeah i think and and a lot of it is
um racially motivated in our criminal
justice system from start to finish i
mean
um most obviously we have higher amounts
of incarcerated people of color than
percentage of
people of color so it's very
disproportionate
and that's something i think that i i
see it at every level
um is that something that you
experienced when you were
without a doubt my prison was typical of
the
demographic breakdown in the federal
prison system it was
it was roughly 50 percent black uh 30
percent hispanic and 20 percent white
and most of the whites were pedophiles
so that that was
that was absolutely typical of of the
entire system
you there how how does someone like you
get on there i mean clearly
you're not a typical you're not the
typical inmate although
with the amount of whistleblowers that
do get i mean you you might start to
have more company in there but
yeah i'm unlike you you're very nice
you're pretty
you know you're you're not you don't
strike me as uh
prison material so how that's 23 months
is a long time
it's a long time for a long time i said
to one of the italians before i answer
your question we were we were on a walk
together and he was a senior
captain in the banana crime family and
had been in prison
much of his adult life so we're walking
around the track and he asked me how
much time i had and i said
i said two years feels like 20 years
and he said two years you could do that
standing on your head and i said i don't
know man i don't know how i'm gonna get
through this
i had only been in about six weeks and
he said let me give you some advice
if anybody asks you how much time you
have
you tell them five years because if they
hear that your sentence is so
short they're going to kick your ass and
so
i began telling everybody that i had
five years and then when it came time to
leave
i was gone what happens is when people
see on the checkout sheet that you're
leaving the next day a gang of people
will come into your cell and just beat
the [__] out of you
just be jealous that it's not them yeah
yeah well
ask me how i got into that prison
there's a story there
so when i agreed to take the plea and
was sentenced
my lawyers asked the judge if she would
send me to a minimum security work camp
well minimum security camps are always
across the street from a higher security
prison because
when there's a riot it's the the campers
who then go across the street to the
main prison
and they do the cooking and the laundry
and the sweeping and scrubbing the
floors and stuff like that
so uh the judge uh asked the prosecutors
any objection they said no no objection
well the thing about the camp is there
are
there are no bars on the windows the
doors are unlocked there are no
fences you're free to come and go as you
please
you're on your honor not to abscond and
frankly most of the prisoners work
in town at the local college you know as
janitors or whatever so it's like a work
release like you get papers
yeah you sleep in the prison but you
work outside okay
so uh the prosecution had no objection
and she said you know
so ordered so i i'd go
prison is the oddest thing you just
drive up to the prison and knock on the
door
and turn yourself in so that's what i
did
i uh a documentary film crew
one of my lawyers um and uh my cousin
and his son all drove me up there and uh
i went to the camp and they said you
have to go across the street to the main
prison first
and check in and then come back over
here i said okay so i went over to the
prison
and uh said i'm john kiriakou i'm here
to turn myself in
and they put me through the metal
detector and frisked me
and then the cop starts to lead me
around to the
back of the prison and i said no no i
said i'm supposed to be over here at the
uh at the camp
and he laughed at me and he said not
according to my paperwork you're not
and i told myself take it easy there's
nothing you can do
if you raise a fuss they're going to put
you in solitary so i didn't say a word
it took me five days before i got access
to a telephone
and i called my lawyer one of my 11
lawyers
the one who i liked and trusted the most
and i said hey
they put me in the actual prison with
the the
mafia dons and the drug kingpins and the
and the perverts
i said what do i do and he said oh my
gosh well
we could file a motion but it'll be two
years before we get a court hearing
you'll be home by then he said i'm sorry
buddy you're gonna have to tough it out
and so i decided you know what you're
trained for this
you've lived in far worse places than
this far more dangerous places than this
i said i'm gonna fall back on my cia
training and i'm gonna make sure
that i remain at the top of the heap i
actually wrote a book about it
that won one of the country's most
prestigious literary awards it's called
doing time like a spy
how the cia taught me to survive and
thrive in prison
and i use these these 20 life
lessons that the cia taught us in
training
to make sure that i was safe and i
was at the top of the social heap and
nobody messed with me
and i'll tell you in 23 months nobody
messed with me
so getting out when you come out of
there i mean now you have obviously a
felony on your record which is a big
deal
um especially for someone who's coming
from an academic and professional
background that's not the kind of thing
that you normally would have to deal
with
so where do you where do what do you do
with that whoa
that's a really great question and it it
was a very difficult thing
you know people don't realize that when
you have a felony
there's no such thing as having paid
your debt to society
you're always a felon you you can't vote
you can't hold a professional license
like how that has anything to do with
professional licenses i have no idea
you can't ever own a gun again i don't
know what it has to do with voting
to be honest i've never
nor did i although i had i had kind of a
good experience with that i can tell you
about in a minute
but um you get out they put me they they
didn't put me in but they assigned me to
a halfway house i
i so angered the the warden by writing a
blog
and smuggling it out of prison that uh
that i didn't get any
halfway house time not a single day i
had to do my entire
sentence not a single day off so
they assigned me to this halfway house
called hope village which has since been
closed
we used to call it either hopeless
village or abandon all hope village
140 men they had one
job posted on the job board and it was
to work at a car wash for 140 men so
you get out and they say you have 90
days to find a job and if you can't
you go back in back in for the next
seven months
and you can't find a job because how can
you possibly find a job
you're a felon how are you going to find
a job so
i was lucky i was luckier than the other
139 guys in there because
i was kind of famous and so
i had a uh a think tank a progressive
think tank that reached out to me and
said
um we can't pay you much we can only pay
you minimum wage
but it's a job so i took that
and then after six months i had to raise
the money for my own salary so i was
doing like gofundme
and all this silly stuff just to make
minimum wage
well minimum wage didn't put food on my
table you know
and so i sort of bounced around from job
to job
i ended up getting a job as a radio host
which was a good fit for me and gave me
the best health insurance i ever had in
my life
but it wasn't enough money to really
make a living
and then finally my wife said screw this
i'm out of here
and she took off so you know i i
here i am i'm fi i'm in my mid-50s and i
had to start all over again
what really saved me and this is unique
to me this is not
i'm far luckier than than any other oh
yeah i'm
far lucky yeah that i am i'm a national
hero in greece
when i when i first got in trouble the
greek uh ambassador
approached me and he said what can we do
to be helpful and i said you could give
me greek citizenship
and he did so here i'm this guy
this you know this the greeks are
fascinated by the cia they always have
been
so here's this greek american cia guy
who made good and blew the whistle and
took it on the chin
because he wanted to do the right thing
and tell the truth and so
um the greek government hired me to
write a new whistleblower protection law
for them
so i went to greece five times in 2015
we came up with the whistleblower
protection law and we presented it to
the
european parliament in brussels so i
testified twice
in brussels before the parliament and
they passed it into law
and then the greek parliament passed it
into law and now it's
the law of the land for the entire
european union well this was covered
in the news in greece oh here's john
kiriakou again
i'll tell you a funny story i arrived i
arrived at the airport
and i hadn't shaven and my hair was like
this because i was flying coach and
i get off and i come out of the doors
from
customs and they're all these camera
crews
with their cameras right and i turned to
look to see oh there must have
been famous on my plane and then they
run up to me
and i i actually started to laugh like
you were like
what is this yeah i look terrible and
why would you guys
want to talk to me well they wanted to
talk about this whistleblower protection
law
because there was a big scandal a
whistleblower blew the whistle
on the minister of defense he had taken
bribes from siemens and
and it was the first time that the law
was actually being used in court
so um after that i i got so much press
coverage
from that that a consortium of greece's
four wealthiest families um put together
a
a private equity fund like a hedge fund
and they asked me to run it
and so i've been doing that since august
and i finally like made it in life
and uh you know made my big comeback but
i'm still a convicted felon here
yeah you know i still get happy you're
greek it's a good thing you're greek huh
good thing i'm greek because if i wasn't
greek i'd still be making minimum wage
someplace right so the greeks
they saved you yeah they did they saved
me